A Guide to the Rosenthal Medieval Manuscript Collection, 9th century-late 14th century
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Rosenthal Medieval Manuscript Collection, 9th century - late 14th century
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9772
This collection consists of 138 manuscripts.
Bernard M. Rosenthal
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased from Bernard M. Rosenthal, San Francisco California, on December 21, 1971.
Scope and Content Information
The Rosenthal Medieval Manuscript Collection was assembled by Bernard M. Rosenthal to serve as examples of the development of Latin script from the ninth to the sixteenth century. In describing the collection, Mr. Rosenthal wrote:
"The collection is primarily a tool, a laboratory, for teaching medieval Latin paleography and codicology. The range is such, however, that it can be used in other disciplines: the musicologist will find a good representation of medieval musical notation, the classicist can illustrate techniques of text identification and critical text editing, [and] the number of legal documents if sufficient for acquiring the basic skills of diplomatics.
"Practically all Western scripts are represented: Carolingian miniscules, Gothic miniscules, various types of bâtarde, cursives, the Italian round Gothic and littera bononiences, the humanistic miniscule and cursive, and the legal hands ranging from the neat deeds of the Bologna notaries to the "illegible" common law hands of 17th-century England. The countries of origin are Italy, Spain, France, Germany, and England.
"Most leaves are vellum, but some of the later ones are paper; sizes range from small 8vo to large folio. The state of preservation varies: many of the leaves have at one time served as covers of archival bundles or book-bindings and now show corresponding traces of use: fading, stains, cut edges, remains of glue, pen-and-ink scrawls, etc. Other leaves are in perfect condition. In all cases, even when the specimen consists of only a fragment of a leaf, there is enough text to establish the characterisitics of the script. The variable quality of preservation and the fragmentary nature of the material reflect the reality which confronts the scholar working with medieval primary sources."
Contents List
- Carolingian minuscule with Rustic Caps, 9th century. (Box 1)
  Fragment from a Lectionarium, with a large decorative capital; rustic caps used for headings.
- Carolingian minuscule with Rustic Caps, 9th century. (Box 1)
  Fragment from a Lectionarium, with three decorative large capitals; rustic caps used for headings.
- Carolingian minuscule, Unidentified text, 9th century. (Box 1)
  Four small fragments removed from the binding of Phillipps MS 16257.
- minuscule, with neumes, 11th century. (Box 1)
  German. Probably from a Gradual or Missal. The marginal notes are in German, in a 15th-century bastarda cursive.
- Carolingian minuscule, ca. 1100. (Box 1)
  Central Europe? Probably from a Lectionary. Particularly interesting because of the very early neumes.
- Carolingian minuscule, 10th/11th century. (Box 1)
  Probably from an Office Book. A rather unusual minuscule; could be of the 11th century.
- Carolingian minuscule, 10th/11th century. (Box 1)
  Germany? Two double leaves from a Missale. The neumes supplied by a later hand (13th century).
- Carolingian minuscule with neumes, 10th/11th century. (Box 1)
  Germany? Probably from a Missale. Neumatic notation is without staves. Some peculiar punctuation marks.
- Carolingian minuscule, 10th/ 11th century. (Box 1)
  Bible fragment (3 Kings, 10). Identified and dated by Professor [Bernard?] Bischoff of Munich University.
- minuscule, ca. 1100. (Box 1)
  Germany? Apparently from a Missale. With non-diastematic musical notation.
- Carolingian minuscule, 10th/11th century. (Box 1)
  Commentary or sermon on the Gospel of Mark, XI/I. Remains of a large decorative initial I.
- Carolingian minuscule, 11th/12th century. (Box 1)
  Responsorium, with musical notation. An unusually elegant script.
- minuscule, ca. 1100 or early 12th century. (Box 1)
  S. German? From an Antiphonale? With non-diastematic neumes. The two fragments are part of the same leaf.
- Insular minuscule, ca. 1100. (Box 1)
  Very similar to the St. Albams Prudentius (Cotton MS Titus), cf. British Museum, Schools of Illumination, part II, pl. 1a and 1b.
- Carolingian minuscule, late 11th century. (Box 1)
  Germany. Probably from a Breviary.
- Small Cursive minuscule, 11th century. (Box 1)
  France? From Isidorus Hispalensis' Etymologiae, XIX. Of considerable paleographic and textual interest.
- minuscule, late 11th century. (Box 1)
  Commentary on the New Testament.
- Late Carolingian minuscule, ca. 1125 - 50. (Box 1)
  Laudatio Phillippi apostoli (laudatio brevis) BHL, 991. With an initial P containing a bird devouring an animal.
- Early Gothic minuscule, late 12th century. (Box 1)
  S. Germany. Four fragments from a Psalter. Many transitional characteristics are in evidence. Some 14th century German marginalia.
- Late Carolingian minuscule, 12th century. (Box 1)
  Italy. From a Missale or Lectionary. A fine large script; note the frequent use of uncial capitals.
- Early Gothic minuscule, 12th century. (Box 1)
  South German? Prologus libri Iesu filii Syrach. With a smaller fragment from the same MS.
- Late Carolingian minuscule, 12th century. (Box 1)
  France? Unidentified prayer. Double leaf.
- Early Gothic minuscule, late 12th century. (Box 1)
  Germany. From a Missale, with neumes. Double leaf. Note the decorative initials and the different decorative patterns.
- Late Carolingian minuscule, 12th century. (Box 1)
  France. Commentary on Psalms 35 and 36. Double leaf.
- Early Gothic minuscule, late 12th century. (Box 1)
  France. Epistle of Saint Gregory to the Bishop of Taranto. Text entirely in French. Note spelling peculiarities; these can probably lead to accurate localization.
- Insular minuscule, Dictionary of Biblical names, ca. 1200. (Box 1)
  England. This type of script is now thought to be the precursor of the Flemish bâtarde.
- Gothic minuscule, ca. 1300. (Box 1)
  France. Unidentified scholastic text with profuse marginal and interlinear annotations by contemporary and later hands, in semi-cursive and cursive. Probably a manuscrit universitaire.
- Gothic minuscule, 12th/13th century. (Box 1)
  France. Unidentified theological text dealing chiefly with the Anti-Christ. Double leaf.
- Transitional minuscule, Priscianus, Grammatica, ca. 1150. (Box 1)
  Italy? The Script is a Carlolingian minuscule already heavily influenced by Gothic.
- Carolingian minuscule, Corpus Juris Civilis, with interlinear notes, 12th century. (Box 1)
  Italy. An unusually early specimen of a Corpus Juris MS.
- Carolingian minuscule, Unidentified text..., ca. 1100. (Box 1)
  Germany? Possibly a commentary on the Benedictine or other monastic rule.
- Chancery minuscule, 1100-1135. (Box 1)
  England (Yorkshire). Notarial document regarding a piece of land. Undated, but in the reign of Henry I.
- Transitional minuscule, ca. 1200 or slighlty later. (Box 1)
  Germany? Graduate with much musical notation.
- Gothica Textualis Formata, 13th/14th century. (Box 1)
  Germany? From a Missale.
- Gothic minuscule, ca. 1250. (Box 1)
  Spain. Breviary with liturgical readings. Musical notation: squarish notes, but no staves.
- Gothic minuscule, Prophetia Malachiae, ca. 1200. (Box 1)
  France. The main text in a large, formal minuscule; the commentary in a script about half as large, probably by the same scribe.
- Gothic minuscule, 13th century. (Box 1)
  Germany? Unidentified devotional text.
- Gothica Textualis, 13th/14th century. (Box 1)
  S. Germany (Austria?). Unidentified vocabularius, amo to amazones. A handsome, fully developed textual gothic minuscule.
- Gothic cursive, 13th century. (Box 1)
  France? Unidentified commentary, apprently on canon law. Note authorities cited in margins: St. Isidore, Basil, Gregory, etc.
- Gothic Textualis, late 13th century. (Box 1)
  France. Unidentified legal text in a small, compressed script.
- Gothic Textualis, late 13th century. (Box 1)
  Unidentified canon law text in a small, much abbreviated roundish Gothic. On the bottom margin: verses on the three marriages of St. Anne.
- Gothic Text Cursive, 13th century. (Box 1)
  France. Unidentified devotional verses: rules for what portion of the Bible to read in a given time of the year.
- Gothica Textualis, 13th century. (Box 1)
  France (Paris). Probably a manuscrit universitaire. Double leaf. See Destrez, Pecia, p. 1.1.
- Gothic minuscule, ca. 1200. (Box 1)
  France (Paris). Natural science text (de aere, vaporibus et eorum condensatione). At foot of page, addenda by a contemporary or somewhat later hand, cursive.
- Gothic Text Cursive, 13th century. (Box 1)
  France? Unidentified scholastic text, probably a commentary. A much abbreviated and compressed text. The underscored portions might be the passages being commented on.
- Gothica Textualis, Roffredo di Benevento, Ordo judiciarius, 13th century. (Box 1)
  Italy.
- Littera Bononiensis, 13th century. (Box 1)
  Italy. Unidentified commentary.
- Small Gothic minuscule, 13th century. (Box 1)
  France. Two leaves from an Old Testament. This kind of small, elegant script was used extensively for Bibles in France and England in the 13th century. 1 Judges, 2 Ezechiel.
- Early Gothic minuscule, early 13th century. (Box 1)
  Germany. Two small framents from a Breviary, fiendishly glued together upside-down by a book binder.
- Gothic Text minuscule, 13th/14th century. (Box 1)
  Law text; extensive use is made of technical abbreviations. A good professional hand, probably German. Apparently written in some haste, hence occasionally almost a cursive.
- Italian Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 1)
  Italy. Unidentified commentary or homiletic text.
- Gothic Text Cursive, 13th century. (Box 1)
  Italy. Vocabularius juris? Perhaps Hugutio de Pisa, Liber derivativus.
- Italian Gothis minuscule, 13th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Unidentified ecclesiastical text. Note the added text in a slightly later cursive: a dialogue on Biblical topics. Double leaf.
- Italian Gothic, late 13th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Perhaps a Summa (Bartholomaeus Pisanus?). Includes De duello, de naufragiis, etc. Double leaf.
- Gothic minuscule, 13th century. (Box 2)
  Italy? Biblical commentary, with interlinear and marginal gloss.
- Gothic minuscule, 13th century. (Box 2)
  Italy? Conessionale. Double leaf.
- Bâtarde Text Cursive, 13th century. (Box 2)
  France. Unidentified devotional text. Double leaf.
- Gothic minuscule, 13th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Apparently a grammatical or philosophical text. The script seems to be rather hasty.
- Gothic minuscule, 13th century. (Box 2)
  Unidentified, probably philosophical text. Extremely abbreviated script.
- Gothic minuscule, mid 13th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Virgil, Aeneis, mostly Book V. Double leaf.
- Gothic Book Cursive, 13th century. (Box 2)
  Unidentified classical verses. The script is rather unusual and the text probably of great interest.
- Gothic minuscule, early 13th century. (Box 2)
  Germany? Probably a Missale, with musical notation. Four leaves. The neumes and their text seem to be by a different hand.
- Insular Notarial Script, 13th century. (Box 2)
  England. 2 documents: they are undated, but were written during the period of Henry III, 1217-1272 or Edward I, 1273-1307.
- Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Unidentified scientific text, possibly relating to the quadratura circuli; other portions mention Pythagoras and mathematical topics.
- Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Germany. Text dealing with delegati, vicarii.
- Rounded Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Northern Italy (Bologna). Corpus Juris Civilis (or last wills). Note instructions to the rubricator on the extreme bottom margin.
- Rounded Gothic minuscule, late 13th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Unidentified legal text (Instrumentum ... debitoris).
- Gothic minuscule, late 13th century. (Box 2)
  N. Italy. Perhaps from Petrus Comestor, Historical scholastica. A very professional Italian Gothic hand.
- Rounded Gothic minuscule, late 14th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Unidentified secular text, with cursive ms notations.
- Rounded Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Classical poem.
- Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Ovid, Metamorphoses, with marginal and interlinear annotations. Manuscripts of this text of such relatively early date are unusual.
- Rounded Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Commentary on Luke.
- Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Missale? A stately script, but probably from a provincial scriptorium. Double leaf.
- Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  France. Breviary?
- Gothic Semi Cursive, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Herbal: canna mellis, Coriandrum, Camphora, etc.
- Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Dante, Divina Commedia. A relatively early example of a Divine Comedy manuscript.
- Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Germany. Missale, with neumes. A fine, almost monumental hand.
- Rounded Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  N. Italy. Index to an encyclopedia, from Ampulla to Apoplexia.
- Gothica Textualis, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Pandectae, xlviii: De nuntiaturis. Probably written by two hands, one recto, one verso. Not what one would call a characteristic law hand.
- Gothic minuscule, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Flemish? Probably a Lectionary. Note the very angular, compressed script. Double leaf.
- Rounded Gothic minuscule, late 14th century. (Box 2)
  Italy. Missale? The music on four-line stabes. A liturgical Italian hand, moving towards the Bolognese.
- Gothic Cursive, 14th century. (Box 2)
  Unidentified text. The unrelated note in the bottom margin is in German.
- Gothic Cursive, ca. 1300. (Box 2)
  France? Unidentified historical text. Double leaf.
- Gothic Cursive, early 14th century. (Box 2)
  France. Probably a scholastic text. An extremely abbreviated script, perhaps by a student.
- Insular Cursive, ca. 1300-1320. (Box 2)
  England. Unidentified text; probably notes from lectures on logic (several mentions of Aristotle). A school-hand, perhaps Oxford or west England.
- Document, early 13th century. (Box 2)
- Document, 1248. (Box 2)
- Document, 1348. (Box 2)
- Notarial Cursive, late 14th century. (Box 2)
  Italy (Pergola near Pesaro). Legal document, executed in the time of Pandolfo Malatesta. On paper, double leaf.
- Document, May 1, 1322. (Box 2)
  England.
- Document, December 6, 1332. (Box 2)
- Document, June 24, 1341. (Box 2)
- Document, July 25, 1392. (Box 2)
- Document, 14th century. (Box 2)
- Beneventan Script, 11th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Southern Italy. Gregorius. Moralia in Job. An outstandingly interesting example of scriptura Beneventana, formerly owned by Prof. E. A. Lowe, who also wrote the leading and definitive monograph on this script.
- Carolingian Minuscule, [late?] 11th century. (Box 3)
  Central Italy. Unidentified text pertaining to the Gospel of Mark.
- Carolingian Minuscule, 10th century? (Box 3)
  From the apocryphal Acta Pauli et Theclae -- the episode of Queen Trifena.
- Carolingian Minuscule, ca. 1125. (Box 3)
  Italy. De officiis presbyteri, and some canons. Note archaic elements in the script.
- Carolingian Minuscule, 11th century. (Box 3)
  Commentary on the seven days of Creation, and, more generally, on the number 7.
- Carolingian Minuscule, ca. 1100. (Oversize V-1)
  De peccato originali. Note archaic script, probably from a provincial scriptorium.
- Carolingian Minuscule, early 12th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Italy. Book of Kings. Fully developed "Carolingian revival" script, which served as basis for the formation of the humanistic script.
- Carolingian Minuscule, 12th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Italy? Probably from a Missale. Note the uncial capitals of some headings.
- Late Carolingian Minuscule, 12th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Unidentified text, perhaps a sermon on the Gospel of John. An exceptionally large script.
- Carolingian Minuscule, with miniature and large caps, ca. 1125-1150. (Oversize V-1)
  Italy. Double leaf from a giant Bible (Book of Job); with a large historiated initial with the figure of Job. Uncial caps are used for the explicit, large ones for the INCIPIT LIBER IOB ... HUS. Faded.
- Late Carolingian Minuscule, early 12th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Italy. Lectio or commentary on the Gospel of Luke. A very elegant, professional script, probably from a major scriptorium. Some 16th-century ricordanze on the bottom margin.
- Early Gothic Minuscule, late 12th century. (Box 3)
  Germany? Two large fragments, probably form an Antiphonal; the fragments seem to be consecutive. Each text line accompanied by music.
- Early Gothic Minuscules, early 12th century. (Oversize V-1)
  France? Deuteronomy, I-II, 4. The commentary in the left column is in a smaller script than the main text. On the extreme right, directions to the rubricator for filling in the titles.
- Transitional Minuscule, ca. 1150. (Oversize V-1)
  Probably from Kings I.
- Late Carolingian Minuscule, ca. 1200. (Oversize V-1)
  Italy? Book of Kings.
- Carolingian Minuscule, ca. 1200. (Oversize V-1)
  Italy. Biblical dictionary? Double leaf. Unusual entry on fol. 2r, dated Pavia 1466: Emi ab hebreo Ange(l?)o ducatus xi... This may refer to the purchase of the present MS. Note the unusual multiple ruling.
- Transitional Minuscule, ca. 1150. (Box 3)
  Italy. Unidentified grammatical text, apparently in the form of a mnemonic verse. Some later interlinear notes in cursive script.
- Gothic Cursive, 13th century. (Box 3)
  Paris. Probably from Aristotle, Metaphysica. Heavily abbreviated script, probably from a "manuscrit universitaire" used by Sorbonne students.
- Monumental Gothic Minuscule, early 13th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Spain. Unidentified Bible commentary.
- Gothic Book Cursive, 13th century. (Box 3)
  France. Probably a fragment from a work of Thomas Aquinas. Double leaf. See Destrez, Pecia, pl. 6.
- Gothic Cursive Minuscule, 13th century. (Box 3)
  France. Unidentified philosophical text or commentary. Double leaf. See Destrez, Pecia, pl. 5.
- Text Minuscule, early 14th century. (Box 3)
  Italy. Bonaguida Aretinus, Summa introductoria super officio advocationis. The script is a transition between Italian Gothic and littera bononiensis. Double leaf.
- Littera Bononiensis, late 13th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Bologna. Double leaf from a law commentary. A very fine example of what seems to be an early type of Bologna law hand.
- Italian Gothic Minuscule, late 13th century. (Box 3)
  Vocabularium juris, from Penitentia to Postulatio.
- Gothic Minuscule, 13th century. (Box 3)
  Italy. Unidentified religious text, possibly from a Tractatus de Vitiis et Virtutibus. Double leaf.
- Monumental Gothic Minuscule, ca. 1300. (Oversize V-1)
  France. Ecclesiasticus, Cap. XXIII, 24 - XXIV, 13.
- Rounded Gothic Minuscule, 14th century. (Box 3)
  Unidentified text, apparently a history of the world, based on the O.T., St. Isidore, Orosius, etc. Double leaf.
- Littera Bononiensis, 13th/14th century. (Box 3)
  Italy. Table of Biblical names. Double leaf.
- Littera Bononiensis, 14th century. (Box 3)
  Italy. Corpus Juris Civilis. The main text surrounded by gloss in smaller script; with added notes in contemporary cursive.
- Literra Bononiensis, 14th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Italy. Corpus Juris Civilis. Note that the size of the script used in the gloss is the same as that of the main text, actually even somewhat larger.
- Gothic Minuscule, late 14th century. (Box 3)
  Italy. Lectionary. Note the penwork decorating the initials.
- Gothic Minuscule, 14th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Italy. Commentary on a medical text.
- Gothic Minuscule, early 14th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Lectionarium.
- Gothic Minuscule, 13th/14th century. (Box 3)
  France. Apparently a commentary on the Old Testament or a history of ancient times. Double leaf.
- Gothic Minuscule, 14th century. (Box 3)
  Italy. "Dominica prima de adventu." Note the strong lateral compression. Half of a double leaf.
- Late Gothica Textualis, 14th century. (Box 3)
  Italy. Legendae sacntorum. This type of clear, rounded Gothic was used immediately before -- and concurrently with -- the humanistic reform.
- Gothic Minuscule, 14th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Flemish. Antiphonale, with music on four-line stave. Some passages in Dutch. Note the later correction slip pasted in.
- Gothic Minuscule, 14th century. (Oversize V-1)
  Germany or Austria. Antiphonale. A vigorous large script. Note the fine penwork in the initial G.
- Insular Cursive, early 14th century. (Box 3)
  England. Statuta Angliae. Part of the text is in French. Double leaf.
- Notarial Cursive, 1366. (Oversize V-1)
  Italy. A very large legal document on two pieces of vellum pasted together.
- Papal Chancery Minuscule, 1354. (Oversize V-1)
  (Avignon). Privileges conferred upon the chapels of Karlberg and Muhlbach in the diocese of Wurzburg, by Innocent VI, November 20, 1354. With an endorsement by the rector of Muhlbach, in German, 1370 (Gothic cursive). Very large folio; without seal.
- Notarial Cursive, ca. 1350. (Oversize V-1)
  Italy. A summary of cases relating to matrimony; some French details might point to Avignon. Note that the verso is blank.
- Document, 1333. (Oversize V-1)
  Spain (Valladolid). Apparently a privilege, granted by King Ferdinand. The accomplished script indicates that the document was executed at the Royal chancery. The lead seal is lacking. This item is also available on microfilm, reel M-205.